so this is the shorter note on utta in
the our huts reflection what appears is
flexibly is only unchecked under which
he calls myself simply for wants of any
other term then Regina's reflection what
appeared effectively is punch upon Donna
content or Sakaya and Sakaya one of the
piers reflexively appears in one way or
another as being and belonging rune
extra temporal changes itself the
petitioner confuses as they are about
does not his self identity of simple
reflection as with a mirror where the
same thing you've seen too many points
of view at once thing itself self same
thing with itself as the subject that
appears in reflection myself ie
I itself the eye that appears when I
so it may not be exactly obvi obvious
you know the simile given here it's kind
of a of course level of like looking at
yourself in the mirror I was hoping you
could explain more about what exactly it
explain more about what exactly it
entails to have a thing to be seen from
two points of view at once may not be
obvious people may think I only see one thing
people may think I only see one thing
the ones view my well in order to
develop to get the notion of that
properly a person needs to needs to
start recognizing what a what a
phenomenon is as in they need they need
to learn how to allow things to arise
and endure and that's the important
aspect here enduring because usually
people regard the presence of something
when you think about it but then if
you're not directly attending it to you
sort of well you forget about it and if
you think about it again you think of it
as if it's a different thing so allowing
thoughts feelings intentions basic alarm
phenomena that has a reason to endure so
for example you can have a certain
enduring mood that you are in
despite the particular manifestations
rather day despite the particular
actions your mood remains the same and
it's the same mood that has been
enduring throughout the day changing on
a particular level while remaining the
same and I say that's important because
only then in relation to to an enduring
phenomena you can practice proper
reflection wherever you can see it's
still enduring even much later if it's
still the same phenomenon which then
brings you to the to the next point of
discernment which is recognizing that
the immediacy of the phenomena is a
point of view in the same sense that
reflecting upon the immediacy of that
phenomena is another simultaneous point
of view which is any it's in the core of
any process of thinking whenever you
think you step back to the green being
able to step back in regard to your own
thoughts in regard to your own actions
means there is a possibility to step
back which means there is that whole
time of reflection that as a Nevada said
of reflection that as a Nevada said
remains perpetual perpetually available
so so you practice reflexing as in your
practice stepping back into it
that doesn't mean you interfere or you
try to change the reason object that's
enduring in front of you but you just
start reflecting upon it while it is
still there and that means seeing that
same thing from two points of view at
once experience reflection
twice immediately in this picture sense
reason their reflection
so that's what you're gonna turn into
like when you even discursively thinking
about something that is already a degree
of stepping back which allows you that
space to look at what you what you've
been thinking about are usually people
are too absorbed with whatever it's in
their immediacy that even the acts of
reflection even elaborate acts of
reflection remain completely they remain
completely unaware of
can you describe exactly what is meant
by experience being immediate well
whatever its present in front of you
what is present within your experience
whatever has arisen there's always some
basis for your thinking for your
intentions for your feelings that basis
is the immediacy your situation
basically that's what that's what
immediacy means because you're always in
a situation that's what would encourage
the mindfulness of the bodily postures
because those are the fundamental setups
of your situation the way your bodies is
deposited in nature so that determines a
whole set of possible intentions and
possible directions
so in the next paragraph he's discussing
the difference between like the
self-identity of a thing like the same
thing versus the idea of itself as the
subject
so I get I guess the assumption it
seemed to me was that maybe a petitioner
conceives his self enduring as the same
thing then kind of adds more than is
actually there
but that's the thing nothing can be
created as imprecision I cannot invent
and create a phenomena that's completely
independent of the five aggregates or
his experience as a whole for his
situation so even the sense of self the
complete mistake of what Regina is is
real as such that thing the petition
takes itself is there it is a phenomenon
and that's when you have point set he
says that it's the self sameness of the
thing that appears in immediacy and
reflection the petitioner confuses for
his self so even that self a petitioner
is there as a phenomenon but the mistake
it's not like negating that that
phenomena the mistake is appropriating
it so proteges needs to do is stop
taking that selfness of a self same
thing seen in reflection and immediacy
at the same time stop taking that self
as his own
moremore achieves that exactly by
reflecting you would see that immediate
and reflection are inseparable as in the
given situation and the pretty much your
ability to be conscious of a given
situation they're they're paired right
to the bone they they just cannot occur
apart from each other they cannot even
be conceived apart from each other so
you realize that any notion of self that
arises arises on account of that
determination so it becomes
inconceivable for it to be mine as in
independent of all this that's in front
of me and it's it's the very lack of
reflection upon that there's the reason
for for petition is still maintaining
the notion of ownership and appropriate
and appropriation
so in the third paragraph Univera
mentioned about how the petition that
assumes that things are mine because of
them whereas sotapanna sees that I am
because things are on and he describes
the significance things presenting
themselves of mine as this significance
or intention or determination mine or
for me is in a sense avoid a negative
aspect of the present thing for existing
phenomena it simply points to a subject in the
it simply points to a subject in the
patina not seeing impermanence or more
specifically not seeing the impermanence
of this ubiquitous determination
deceives himself into supposing that
there actually was a subject self
independent of the object which later
has a dizzy Symphony well understands
isn't merely the positive aspect of this
number that which is for me in this way
and where we've seen the petunias
experience punch upon anaconda has a
negative aspect subject and a positive
aspect the object so
it seems to me then that
shirring - is partly talking about how
to attend things proper so just he's
talking about thing he's pointing to a
subject but one has to figure out how to
understand something
pointing I guess without looking where
it's pointing so to speak well it is
that it's that that's what sense of
appropriation is bound with things
appear for for a purpose for something
and the the utmost the most general or
the most fundamental the subtlest
purpose is even if a thing is completely
without any practical purpose
it still has a purpose to appear for an
input to Gina would finish that
assumption because he already has that
gratuitous view of me and I end so he
would just ah it appears for me and that
immediately already implies the entire
appropriation of the entire sense place
for example because if you were to see
that nothing can appear without
functioning physical senses working
there that beyond your control things
cannot it couldn't appear for you but by
not seeing that then you just naturally
with the grain assume that the
appearance the mere appearance of things
well they might not be mind but at least
these perceptions are mine these the
sight sound smell taste touches a mind
because they feel for me they don't feel
for something anybody else so is the
assumption of that me that he's not
really justified in making that's why
once the assumption of self view is
undone it cannot come back because there
was never room for it in the first place
but not knowing that you actually
created that that there room and as the
Buddha said that mistake that that
assumption is beginningless so there was
no first point before which person
wasn't ignorant and they became ignorant
and develop the self view so all the it
shouldn't be there if it's fully
understood it won't be there but by not
knowing that you you place it there you
assume it's being there
hence the the being raised result of
your assumption as in bar becomes group
enough so when we say for me it sounds
like you're saying it's kind of a more
fundamental thing like a thing being
like mine in the same direction yeah
yeah yeah it's it's just it's it's being
man is the extension of for me being for
me
because being for me implies the
possibility of being mine which means
you could regard for me as a very very
subtle form of conceiving as mine
already because you at least conceived
it as it possible to be yours
so he goes on to clarify further with
regards to the fact that the cottages
experience has the subject and the
object but care is needed for in fact
the division subject object is not a
simple negative positive division if it
were only the positive would be present
as a distinct phenomenon and negative
the subject is not present at all say
something like this but the subject is
in a sense phenomenon it is an existing
phenomenal negative and negative that
appears that the two jannat asserts the
present reality of itself
irreplaceable being that I am in fact is
that the intention or tarnish in mind
pointing to the subject it's a complex
structure involved in the region the
center is not simply a negative in
relation to a positive object it is a
master over the object is thus kind of a
positive negative a master who does not
appear explicitly but who or somehow
nevertheless this it is this master
engages in reflection is seeking to
identify in vain missed elusive mastery
of subject of objectivity rigorously
distinguished from the reflexive power
control or choice as besides involuntary
action by the to Gina so it's
I guess it's more than just like having
a few people get mystical about one
sends herself you know they say that I
am the knower the witness at the same
time they're bringing up that idea of
them as a witness to that extent they
they have this weird hybrid you know
positive and negative simultaneous thing
that's why it is and it seems kind of
liable to mystification it does seem
that go beyond both domains well it is
it's it's it's structurally supported so
to speak through that implication of
ownership you end up also testing sort
of implying that there is the owner
because why why would then everything be
manifested for with the purpose of being
on and for somebody for something if
there is nobody there so then even
because that's a glitch that that
mistake is beginningless means a
petition that doesn't get to think from
the right point of view first and then
develops a mistake
he's the mistake so that's why he can't
see so even when he thinks about or there is
so even when he thinks about or there is
nobody there he takes that as that which
is there as a self-centered phenomenon
so in that sense you can you can yeah
you can mr. fight you can you can deny
it you can do whatever you want with it
and you were still will be regarding it
is mind as and as my sense of self
and what I wanted to ask about this in
that last sentence from the note again
it goes this delusive mastery of subject
of our object must be rigorously
distinguished from a reflexive power of
control or choice that is exercised
voluntarily in an action by Futuna
neuron alight
how it how is it exactly that one can
make choices about things you know it
seems like I am I am choosing all at the
same time it seems he's saying the are
hard is also making choices but for him
it's it's a different affair well that's
what's in common to both other hand the
mutagen it's the choice the power of
choice its structural it belongs to five
aggregates it states it's the power it's
the power revealed through the
simultaneous theories and options
different possibilities that determine
what the present thing is so that's
that's something that both Buddha Jenna
and another hand have but the problem
with with having that mistake of
ownership you neva tably that that kind
of because choices are relatively subtle
in comparison to other course of
perceptions and so on so it will
inevitably gravitate to a worlds that
center of the assume itself as in I am
making these choices I am deciding this
over I'm deciding that and then it just
keeps reinforcing them that sense of
self because because that kind
notion of mastery needs maintenance and
that maintenance is provided through
like choosing preferences up on this or
over over over that and so on but our
hunt removes ownership in regards to the
whole structure of the five aggregates
you have the experience as a whole
thus no amount of volition and
intentional action and thinking can
induce that mistake again because he is
fully penetrated and fully understood it
and and so that it's simply there is no
room for any sense of self or any
ownership that to any extent the last
thing I want to bring up see
bass are talking about the elusiveness
of that subject
he writes infinity
but positive negativity of the subject
which is what concerns us here but no
means a simple affair the subject
presents itself at the same time
certainly more elusive it no there's no
less real than the object so is our is
our task here to make this self not
anymore it isn't the task is to stop to
learn how to see that sense of self as
elusive how to see it as an elusive
phenomenon the task is to stop trying to
overly define it or see it as a thing
that's object of your perception because
it's always in the background because
for as long as you have those
assumptions that you can find it on the
level of perceiving it directly you are
disqualifying yourself from actually
being able to see it because it can only
be seen on its own terms and those terms
are the terms of an elusive phenomena in
ambiguous background phenomena and you
have to start seeing it as such and then
you realize you don't need to see it in
any more defined manner because whether
it's an elusive phenomena whether it's a
cliff and I'm going to run it to the
phenomena in the immediacy or the
reflection therefore the foreground the
background phenomena is there it doesn't
matter what kind of it it is and that's
what you want to be discerning and
that's how you can start including that
sense of self no matter how I loose
videos